this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
c-radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
hi all welcome to software engineering
radio this is your host kanchan shringi
today we welcome Jeff Perry to our show
Jeff is a career coach with experience
in many engineering and Technology
Fields prior to being a career coach
Jeff has worked on designing and
building products and processes as a
software engineer a mechanical engineer
and a manufacturing engineer Jeff now
aims to help software engineers make
intentional career transitions while
leveling up their skills and also
balancing their lifestyle desires
welcome to the show Jeff is there
anything else you'd like to highlight in
your bio you know you shared a lot of
great stuff there conscient I'm just
excited to dive into our conversation
and maybe we can share more of the
stories we go along I'm excited here
absolutely as we're going to talk today
the focus is going to be on how we as
Engineers can be intentional and
proactive when evaluating and pursuing
our career options
like you said we hope to discuss
examples as well in the show note I will
link to many episodes that we have done
on this topic in the past or related
topics that will be useful to listen to
as well
so jumping right into it Jeff the first
question would be what to evaluate
meaning what are the career options for
a software engineer well that's such a
broad thing because software Engineers
can be so versatile in the areas that
they can take their careers right so
think about just the different types of
technology that can be involved in
different languages different sorts of
architecture different applications if
they want to work on products or
Services security quality all sorts of
different things then we can talk about
different paths that they might take
within that if they want to go a deep
technical path going towards
architecture or principal engineer or
maybe they want to go on a leadership
Direction being a software lead a
manager director CTO CIO something like
that there's also options for people
that go from into sales or Solutions
engineering really working very close
mostly with customers and solutions and
different things like this and be in
product management using the knowledge
that they have of the technology but
getting closer to creating products
there's so many different options here
which is part of what I think makes
Engineers so excited but also can
sometimes get them scared about how do I
make that decision with so many options
in front of me and how do we move
through all of that uncertainty with
where Technologies and opportunities and
different things are going to go there's
a lot in front of us so we need to
figure out what's right for me as an
individual and I hope that's a lot of
the things that we can flesh out as far
as how do we move through that process
as we go through our conversation today
that makes a lot of sense and I was just
thinking that this would be most
confusing to someone that's right out of
school how would you advise someone in
that category to evaluate perhaps they
start with evaluating the internships
and other offers that they have
yeah well first of all if they have
options and internships that's great the
fact that they have options is fabulous
now coming right out of school recognize
that there's so much that you don't know
and even if you're 5 10 20 years into
your career there's still so much that
you don't know you will never know all
the things because all the things
continue to grow and expand so someone
who's coming right out of school it's
really first of all just saying how can
I get experience get exposure get growth
opportunities that I can learn things
faster you've gone through the whole
school experience maybe you've gone
through a university there are plenty of
people entering the software World from
boot camps and other situations or maybe
they're self-taught as well in different
respects no matter what but we need to
sink our teeth into something and so
evaluating the options that may or may
not pay the very best but what
opportunity is going to give you the
most exposure
to different opportunities to different
Technologies and different methodologies
so that you can learn the fastest that's
probably the most important thing early
on your career and something you want to
establish early on and continue on
throughout your career is how can I
learn learn and grow at this stage so if
you have multiple options some may pay
differently than others but don't make
that the only factor that you consider
the experience and the value and what
you are going to learn through that
process as you're looking at the
different options in front of you how
does that change as you proceed on your
journey so let's say I am somebody with
say seven years of experience how should
my Approach change at this point yeah so
at this point I find that a lot of
people are starting to look at okay I've
had multiple experiences usually you've
been touching multiple different types
of Technologies over the years and
you've maybe gone into leading projects
if not people at this point and taking
the lead technically in various
circumstances but now people at this
stage a few years into their career
they're starting to think deeper as far
as where they want to go in terms of the
type of roles that are important to them
do they want to go deeper into the
technological expertise they want to go
into that principal engineer route or
architecture route type thing or do they
want to consider
leading teams do they like those
experiences leading teams and projects
mentoring other engineers and having
those sorts of growth experiences do
they want to perhaps shift towards
products so this is a lot of times uh
defining point and it doesn't need to be
the only one but it's one of those
periods where you've got a little bit of
experience under your belt you've worked
on multiple teams if not multiple
companies on multiple products and
services at this time and so you've got
a lot more to bring to the table and
things that can inform your decisions at
this point as far as which direction
might be the the best fit for you and so
trying to chart that path and go deeper
in a particular area of focus and the
path that you want to take at this point
so you did talk about you know you might
probably worked in multiple teams how
does that play a role versus you as an
individual and you being part of a team
yeah so it plays a role obviously
everyone's experience is different but
even if someone has been in the same
company for the first five seven years
of their experience there's no way these
days that the team that they worked on
and the products and the technology that
they worked on is exactly the same for
that entire time because things continue
to grow progress there's new projects
and people come in and out of teams or
maybe you might get shifted to a team
people have different feelings about
reorganizations that happen at
organizations so even if you're in the
same company you're going to work on
different teams and really what that
does is it gives you different pieces of
exposure and you have different
opportunities to take on different
levels of responsibility for how you
move through projects so those early
years you're probably really taking a
lot as far as other people assigning the
work that you're doing and you're maybe
a lot more reactive in terms of the type
of work that you're doing but later on
as you develop expertise and you have
different experiences you may be raising
your hand and seeking out different
sorts of experiences where you can apply
your unique skill sets to the betterment
of the team and the organization so that
everyone can benefit from that better
so so far the you know your
recommendation was focus on gaining
experience learning getting more
responsibility working on different
kinds of projects interacting with
different kind of people
but now let's say I'm somebody with
close to 15 maybe more than 15 years
experience
what should I do now
you know do I start to have some kind of
a plan or should I already have had a
plan what about building a reputation
for myself what about compensation what
about work-life balance yeah so all
those factors that you mentioned
absolutely we should consider those at
every step along the way and it's this
weird balance between trying to be what
I'd say intentional or Proactive or
deliberate versus also letting things
emerge and and letting opportunities
come your way
because at no point whether you're at
the beginning of your career or five to
seven years in or 15 years in are you
going to have this Crystal Ball moment
where you have everything mapped out in
front of you where it's like this
magical treasure map of x marks the spot
and you have every step along the way I
mean people ask all the time where do
you want to be in five years
you can answer that with the best of
your knowledge today
but whether or not that turns out to be
exactly where you're at you know that
may or may not be true right even if you
are giving the best answer you possibly
can so later in your career though again
it's another sort of mental emotional
strategic shift from how do I broaden
exposure to how do I expand influence
right and this influence that people are
trying to have again can happen in
multiple different angles where if they
went the Deep technical path a lot of
times they're trying to expand influence
in how I deliver high level deep
technological expertise on the
architecture of principle engineer type
roles where I can really be the leader
on the technology side be able to put
things together and Lead teams to
that success on the other side it may be
more strategic connecting more with the
business and the technology on the
leadership side as far as do I want to
be a director of engineering go towards
the CTO type role or VP of engineering
all sorts of titles that that could look
like right but do I really want to go on
that and build those teams and either
scale that in a startup or obviously
companies and the types of things
they're going to be working on can be
vastly different but in any case a lot
of times the shift is towards how do I
expand my influence how do I protect the
compensation how do I deliver the value
that is this combination of all the
experiences that I've had so far and how
do I find ways that I can apply that in
unique ways but that are still going to
give me growth opportunities like you
don't
you still don't want to be complacent
and content with hey I've learned
everything and now I know everything and
now I can just operate operate
still continue to have that drive to be
curious to learn and grow because
technology will continue to change but
you're at this point where you can kind
of have this influence and stewardship
and and really grow other people and
give that experience to others and help
grow grow them along the path along with
you
it's a couple of follow-up questions
you're very rightly sir I don't have
anything to debate that as my experience
but you said you know even if you
answered what you would like to do in
five years that most likely you will not
hold true but should you even try to
answer that is there benefit in trying
to think through it yeah so here's how I
think about this I work with Engineers
all the time on Career Clarity ideas as
far as like what's really important to
them where do they want to take their
careers
now a couple different things again it's
not like this magical treasure map but
what we can think of as far as those
things that are really important to us
is maybe we can map out a North star
right a direction that we want to take a
Guiding Light and these can take the
forms of the types of companies the
types of environments we want to be in
the types of Technologies also answering
questions what do I want to learn
right at every stage but it can also
take a form maybe another analogy that
people can relate with it's like a set
of filters so you have some things that
might be really important to you can you
use those items whether that's
compensation work-life balance types of
Technology what does the role look like
what's the depth of technology versus
the leadership opportunities I'm going
to have all those different things that
you map out as far as that are important
to you and when opportunities come your
way recruiters are reaching out or
you're reaching out to companies that
might be you might be interested in can
you use that set of criteria that you've
established
as far as these are the things that I'm
really interested in that I want to try
that I want to learn these things that
are important to me can I use that as
filters so that when I'm evaluating
opportunities you can say hey does this
meet those criteria if so great let's
continue to explore that if not well
then don't waste your time or anyone
else's time let's continue forward
without that but I find a lot of people
instead of even trying to Define
anything they say I can't see the future
so we don't try and do anything and so
we just kind of let our careers come to
us
and what that means is we are fully
reactive to what's going to happen and
so if we don't chart our path then
someone else will chart it for us right
but but I like to say or use the old
story maybe people are familiar with
Alice in Wonderland right the old movie
and and book at one point Alice is lost
in the Wonderland and in the dark forest
and she comes to a fork in the road and
she finds this other character the
Cheshire Cat right and the cat and she
are talking she asked the cat which path
should I take because there's multiple
paths to take there and the cat asks
well where are you trying to go and
Alice says well I don't know and to
which the cat replies well if you don't
know where you're going any path will
get you there right so if we at least
have an idea of where we're trying to go
and who we're trying to become then in
the moments you know today in the
present we can take steps and take
actions in accordance with where we're
trying to go and also another way I'd
put it is who we're trying to become as
a person as a professional right the
traits that we want to build and the
skills we want to build along the way
sometimes it has some other the
constraints you know example immigration
processing so in your experience has
that changed how people approach their
careers
it has I've worked with a lot of people
who have dealt with that they're trying
to work through Visa constraints and
trying to go through the Green Card
process here in the U.S and different
things and it does constrain options
because not all companies and
opportunities
are willing to sponsor and things like
that which means that a lot of times
people need to focus on in some cases
larger companies they're the ones who
often have those processes for
immigration and sponsorship and things
figured out
and it so it is a constraint it's a hard
reality and it's something we need to
work through but that doesn't mean that
we need to throw all options and those
other questions and things that are
important to us out the window they've
still found that people can still grow
great careers and have great
opportunities
even perhaps within a limited scope for
a while and then finally eventually get
that green card process and you know the
shackles are sort of off and they can do
whatever they want professionally and
and that opens up opportunities of even
entrepreneurship or some startups and
things which might not have been
possible before but all the way along
it's still asking those questions even
within the role that I'm at even if
you're not changing the actual job or
company that you're in how can you even
take micro steps to take on some new
challenges try a new project learn a new
technology raise your hand and take on a
new responsibility see a need that the
organization has and see if you can fill
it in a new way to grow those skills
those capabilities that you want to have
now and in the future along the way
thanks Chef so you did bring up
everybody's unique proposition you
mentioned that why is that important and
in your you know as you've talked to
people do you have examples on when that
became important and how did someone
develop it yeah these these unique value
propositions are important and by the
way we're talking a lot here and and
there's a lot to go through and so I
want to share for the software
engineering radio listeners I've got a
whole set of resources on some of the
topics that we're talking about here
that people can go grab at
www.engineeringcareer accelerator.com se
radio they can go grab some free
resources around some of these topics
that we're talking about here because
they're anything like me they're
probably doing something else while
they're listening to a podcast out on a
walk or exercising or out on a drive or
something put that on the show notes for
sure right right so make sure that they
get those resources but going back to
this whole idea like how do we recognize
our own unique value proposition well
first of all recognize that it changes
and adapts and grows over time right as
we have new responsibilities we have new
opportunities these things grow and
develop but as it stands right now one
of the tools that's in that resource
that I shared there that I really love
pointing people to and helping people I
would say discover for themselves as
something called the Genius Zone okay
as Engineers there's a lot of things
that people are probably really good at
right they have a lot of skills you know
we can talk about all sorts of technical
skills but maybe they have soft skills
and things like this like these are
things that they're very good at they
can lead projects they can develop
websites that can create apps like
whatever that is where they have these
great skills
but a genius zone is something that
perhaps is a little bit more unique to
you
you can look at it as a combination of
skills so maybe you've worked on certain
types of Technologies and a combination
that perhaps few people have and so that
gives you a unique approach to how you
approach these problems maybe worked
across different industries that combine
in a unique way I've had some people
worked on finance side Finance
technology and real estate technology
and bringing that together and so some
of the ways that the Technologies are
trying to use those things they have a
unique perspective and they've been on
the technology side and perhaps on the
user side and so they have a unique
perspective in their ability to bring
value to a company that's trying to do
some of those things right
but in any case what we'd call this is
like a personal brand it's it's really
being able to communicate who you are
what you can do and how that maps to
potential needs of an employer or if
you're an entrepreneur a client or
potential client or group of people so
that you can map and show them and
communicate how you deliver value as you
understand what their needs are right
and this is kind of the essence of what
a personal brand is like who are you
what can you do what are you kind of
known for that people can really utilize
that value in a unique way do you have
any examples of how you might have
helped someone communicate this or even
realize it for themselves and how did it
change their options absolutely so
here's a couple examples one the client
I was working with where she was an
experience level engineer a PhD level
engineer she went deeper than technology
and she was in a consulting company that
people were coming to them and she would
was deep in the tech with all the client
projects that they're working on but she
recognized that she had some
opportunities to get involved in
leadership and managing the projects and
interacting with clients and she
recognized that she loved doing that
work more so than just being deep deep
in the technology all the time all day
every day
and she had some real skills in that and
so she started exploring what are these
things you know how do I map these
things because she had the Deep
technology expertise but she also had
some broad technological expertise and
so she started thinking of what are some
of the different ways that I could apply
this she didn't consider for a long time
until we had some conversations and she
had some conversation with other people
that like technical project management
and program management might be a
potential fit for her
where she could really connect the
technological experience that she had
with the project management and working
with the people and bringing teams
together and those resources in a really
effective way where that really litter
up where she really enjoyed that and so
she went on that path and eventually did
that and and started working at a
National Lab doing some of that work
right so that's one experience and other
experience is someone who experienced
software engineer
probably 15 to 20 years into his career
but he'd had some troubling times along
the way and so what he said to me is he
said I'm trying to find my happy place
in my career
and he didn't know what that meant it
was pretty vague it was it was really
interesting but here's said I'm trying
to find a way that I can really enjoy
where I'm at and he thought originally
that what that meant was that he needed
to make a career shift to a new job okay
but actually what that meant is he
needed to connect with his genius Zone
which he realized was more on the taking
really ambiguous projects Greenfield
projects brand new not a lot of
definition around that and building the
technology and the business processes
around that to be successful from
beginning to end rather than a lot of
the experiences that he had had where he
wasn't really thriving when he was just
kind of in a quality maintenance mode
there's a challenge there's a ticket
that comes in needs to fix that that
wasn't anything that really excited him
and something that he found a lot of
fulfillment in but he had some unique
skills and he'd been able to see that
over the course of his career and
working on those Green Field ambiguous
projects putting definition around them
and helping them kick off successfully
and so he was able to find those
opportunities within his current role in
ways that he could do that and build
some more rigor into that process and
then eventually did actually make a
career transition to a new company where
he could do even more of that and
continue to ask this question how do I
deliver the greatest value in my
organization into my team he shifted
some of his mindset around that so A
couple of follow-ups there when do you
actually start thinking in this way of
what is your personal brand Are there
specific events that trigger that
introspection that's one question and
the second one is when you call it
personal brand a lot of software
development is collaborative you had the
example of the engineer who was actually
thinking of becoming a technical program
manager so there's a lot of
collaboration involved scrum devops you
know work on the success of the team as
opposed to have the individual so what
does that mean to have a personal brand
where a lot of your work and impact is
really performed in teams
yeah great question so as far as is
there a catalyst that gets people
thinking about personal brand well
perhaps listening to a podcast episode
like this and anytime the the idea comes
up maybe it gets you thinking what is my
personal brand do I even know can I
communicate that to anyone
right now and so if the answer is no
then that should be a catalyst that
maybe there's some work that you need to
do and you can spend as much or as
little time on this as as you want to
right invite you to
to spend some time because it's it's
answers worth having for you at every
stage of your career and at every stage
I like to think of the analogy of
building our careers kind of like we're
building a product or service and
Technology like we move through
iterations right or prototypes MVPs and
all these different stages we're never
quite done with becoming who we're going
to be as a professional but if we can
consider hey I'm not a finished product
yet but what's the next experiment
what's the next set of data I can
collect what's the next thing I want to
try and what's the next
prototype I want to build in my career
can I think about that next iteration
then that can help us you know sort of
Define some of these paths along the way
and then I'm trying to remember you
asked two questions in there we're
talking about catalysts for personal
branding I'm trying to remember what
that second one was the second one was
just what does it mean to have a
personal brand where so much of the work
is done as part of a team yeah great
question so within that I think there
could potentially be a branding as a
team and as an individual because you
don't want to necessarily say hey I'm
the awesome person on the team that did
this this and this but we also need to
recognize that every person in the team
is an individual and brings unique value
and skills and abilities so that the
whole team can be successful and so the
collaboration and the personal brand
maybe internally to your team is like
what are you known for as you think
about optimizing the skills on your team
whereas a lot of software teams can be
kind of interoperational they can cross
paths and they can share a lot of the
workload and different sorts of tasks
that they can do but there may still be
areas that some people specialize or
take on certain responsibilities and
sort of take on this is my role because
this is where I'm doing my best work for
the team so even within the team you may
have a personal brand or maybe within
just your company or organization at
large singing about how do people
describe you what do people come to you
for how do you deliver your highest
value to the organization if you can
answer those questions kind of
internally and so it's not making you
separate from the team it's like how can
I actually contribute best to the team
given the experience in the skills that
I bring to the table and the things that
I really enjoy doing because if you're
enjoying doing more of your work then
you're probably going to be doing better
work that brings me to my next question
you talked about how you're known in the
company versus the industry so what's
more important like is do you pick and
choose or do you figure out how to do
both I think you can do both absolutely
and I love the concept of yeah we should
be growing and developing a nourishing
relationships internal to our companies
but also continue to grow and see what's
outside of there because people outside
of your current organization are doing
things differently there's different
technologies that are being used and
developed there's different people that
you can learn from and so both internal
and external to your organization we
should be connecting learning finding
mentors and people that we can learn
from along the way and as far as the
personal branding aspect hopefully we
can find ways to both deliver value
internal to our organization absolutely
if they're paying our paycheck and
delivering our compensation we need to
be delivering appropriate value there
here but there's ways you can do that in
the industry at large whether that's
sharing resources coming on podcasts
blogging sharing things engaging on
social media LinkedIn other things
creating other projects maybe you have
side projects and things that you're
really interested in that I see amazing
things that software Engineers are doing
all the time outside of perhaps their
main mode of employment to deliver value
to the industry at large and to share
things about that help other people in
various respects
so some of this was covered in episodes
281 and 245 as I mentioned earlier I
will put that in the show notes the
links to these other episodes
but especially with respect to the last
few years and especially with a lot more
remote working do you see that the means
of achieving this has changed in some
ways
I would say it's only accelerated right
so going through covid and expanding
remote options to deliver value for
people and organizations and the way
that people are more and more willing to
connect no matter where you are in the
country or around the world right I
think it's only accelerated some of
these things where you don't necessarily
need to be on site with the people that
you might be collaborating with or
connecting with I think the expansion of
social media platforms and the one that
I'm most connected with and use the most
in the professional context which I
think is what we're mostly talking about
here is LinkedIn LinkedIn continues to
grow in the engagement that people are
having on there and how people are
finding new opportunities collaboration
partners and all sorts of things but
your ability to share and be I don't
want to necessarily use the word
influencer but a Creator and someone who
shares and contributes to the community
Unity is amazing because only one
percent of people who have LinkedIn
accounts actually share content on a
weekly basis so if you share just
something a few times a month suddenly
you're in the top one percent that
doesn't take that much right and so all
sorts of different ways that we can find
ways to share it and so I think the
modes of operation maybe you haven't
necessarily changed but I think they've
just accelerated in many cases thanks
Jeff so I wanted to talk now more about
some more catalysts in terms of thinking
about brand or skills so you had an
example whereas you know talking to this
engineer where he was thinking of a
career shift initially and you kind of
guided him towards what his genius Zone
was and what he could potentially
contribute within his company itself but
there must be a time where you start
thinking about what's the best way to
grow you know is it towards leadership
positions or is it a completely you know
horizontal shift in a different area or
acquiring different skills so do you
have examples where people have
struggled with this you know in terms of
has someone asked the question hey
should you know I I've done reasonably
well at being a software engineer I have
done lots of projects I've LED projects
and now I like to figure out if I should
become a manager or should I do
something else because I do want to keep
making progress do you have any such
examples of a struggle yeah absolutely
because I mean even just that question
alone should I stay closer to technology
or should I go deeper into management
and Leadership and things that's a big
question that a lot of Engineers have
and trying to figure out not just if I
should do that but also there's a
component of timing right because
any path could be right for you but
sometimes the timing isn't necessarily
right for either your organization or
for you personally as well and so
there's a lot of different things to
consider so some of those questions you
might start asking yourself especially
if you're considering management or
leadership is recognizing that a shift
to a role like that is a complete shift
as far as your focus of the value that
you deliver in your role right because
as a technological engineer an
individual contributor your main value
is delivered with the technology that
you deliver whether the the code that
you write the products that you're
creating and collaborating with your
team as a leader you deliver value as
you enable others to deliver that
technological value
you need to be willing to step away from
a lot of the Hands-On work and sometimes
there are perhaps lead roles and other
things where you're sort of in a hybrid
role where you're still you know deep
into the technology but taking on some
of those management and Leadership
responsibilities as well different
companies structure that in different
ways and call those different names and
so we don't need to get too much into
the semantics there but it's always
asking yourself the question at these
Crossroads whether that's an opportunity
that is placed in front of you or as you
feel like I think of in terms of you're
asking about a catalyst think of
different stages of our career as kind
of like a inverted s-curve where we get
into a new opportunity there's sort of a
steep growth phase then eventually we
start to Plateau out where we feel like
hey I've learned I now feel like I'm
operating at a high level but I don't
feel like I'm being pushed and grown
anymore so feeling that Plateau feeling
is a great catalog list an indicator
that hey perhaps there's something there
that I need to explore try something new
whether that's in my current role
organization or something else and again
A lot of times we're just trying to
experiment and see get some data along
the way to see what might fit before
perhaps we do a full commitment to A New
Path so that's certainly the impact you
know an intrinsic desire as well to have
greater impact greater influence but
compensation has to play a role in this
as well can we chat a little bit about
that
absolutely but everyone values
compensation a little bit differently at
different stages of their life as well
one of the big things that people are
doing is I mean it can be easy to
compare what I'm hearing that my peers
and my same company or other companies
are making in different things but
compensation across roles is not equal
if roles are not equal in terms of the
value that you're delivering and also
what is that taking from your life right
so you could be making an astronomical
amount of money but if you literally
have zero time to be with your friends
family loved ones and work on other
things that are really important to you
or maybe it's suffering in your health
is that increased compensation really
worth that right and so each person is
going to be a little bit different there
but absolutely when we're trying to
consider compensation I'm big though on
everyone being able to be paid fairly
for where they're at and we can think
about how do we negotiate appropriately
whether in our current role that we're
at if you've been at your role and
you're seeing other people come in and
you're hearing maybe of inflated
salaries absolutely you should be asking
yourself
hey can I get up to that same level too
or Beyond if I've been around for a
while a few years someone gets hired at
a compensation level above me there's no
reason why you shouldn't be asking those
questions on whether or not you can get
that same pay bump too as we've seen
compensations increase across the
software engineering industry the last
couple years especially
but you may think about hey if this
company that I'm at just doesn't have
the ability to compensate you for the
level of impact and value that you bring
to the table then you may need to find
another organization that has the
capabilities to compensate you in a
different way as well so absolutely we
should be considering and balancing the
compensation that we want to take care
and live the lifestyle that we want
balance with actually living that
lifestyle instead of only living for
work right so how do you evaluate that
though you don't know you can guess
potential trade-offs but you don't
really know so how much of it is really
fear of the unknown and how do you
overcome that yeah so uncertainty can be
a huge Factor as people are trying to
make decisions I love this quote from
psychologists by the name of Virginia
satyr she says that people often prefer
the certainty of misery to the misery of
uncertainty
right and so as we're evaluating
potential options if we wanted to take
on a new role or things like this yes
there are things about that that we
won't fully know until we get into it
right that's just the nature of it and
it's the nature of life like we will not
be able to map out what everything is
going to look like if we did life would
be a lot less challenging but also
probably a lot more boring if that were
the truth if we actually had a crystal
ball and could see the future but
as we are moving through this process
and trying to say how do we make these
decisions we just have to have a little
bit of for lack of a better word faith
that we can make the best decision based
on the information that we have right
now
if we're considering other companies and
things we can collect more data online
if we're talking about compensation
there's all sorts of compensation data
levels dot FYI is a great place for
software Engineers to compare different
companies and different roles and what
that looks like as far as what
compensation levels are these days total
compensation other things salary.com
Glassdoor all sorts of other places that
you can compare on the compensation
level data but also asking those
questions it might not be quite as
quantitative but more qualitative as far
as quality of life and different things
that we consider having those
opportunities whether you're
interviewing in the company or you can
reach out to a few people in a potential
company or in a different organization
your existing company whatever that
transition that you're considering
making right now can you have a few of
those conversations with people who
understand and know and hear and and
talk about those considerations at the
same time as you go into a new situation
can you set up your approach to working
in that with setting boundaries and
things that are appropriate to you and
the things that are important to you
rather than just getting swept up and
caught up and saying yes to every single
thing that you do I think even within
the same role or opportunity or company
two people can have a vastly different
experience depending on how they
approach their work and setting up those
relationships and those processes and
the way that they go about doing that
with people so we get to control some of
that and also we need to collect data as
much as we can about those things that
we're trying to make decisions about
so in talking to people or software
Engineers you know I can think of few
key transitions you know senior to lead
or when you go to a manager or from an
individual contributor or even from lead
to architect it's more than just
technical skills at this point there's a
lot of communication skills involved
there's new things that you wouldn't
even know are going to be expected of
you so do you have any examples of
people who have navigated these key
transitions or some other key
transitions yeah absolutely so these
sorts of roles just one person who I was
working with who who's an experienced
engineer about five years into his
career and he'd found himself really
taking on that lead technical role and
he wasn't even necessarily looking for
it but a few months into us doing some
work together as he was trying to
improve how he balances his work and
life and the things that are important
to him he had the position opportunity
come to him to become that engineering
manager for the first time moving from
that senior engineer to engineering
manager for the first time and so
suddenly now he was taking on a
responsibility for I think it was six
other engineers and the team and the
responsibilities on a global team right
but the truth was is that he'd already
been doing a lot of that similar work
already and I think that internal to
companies a lot of times when these new
opportunities come our way it's because
people get those opportunities when
they're already sort of filling that
role they've already sort of Taken on
hey I'm willing to go the extra mile
help the other people when they need it
show that I can deliver that increased
technical value and Mentor the people
around me so they've already sort of
Taken on that role that increased
responsibility for the projects and
raising their hands when something new
needs to get down and there's a new
responsibility that someone needs to
take they're already looking for and
taking those responsibilities this was
absolutely true of him and so the formal
process of him going through that which
by the way he still needed to negotiate
as he got this new opportunity and
increased responsibility still needed to
negotiate the compensation level to go
back to that topic which was a hard
thing because sometimes internally
companies don't always value those
shifts as much as if they were bringing
in and I find that very interesting that
that can often be the case but he had to
fight for an increase in compensation in
this case even though he was taking on
additional responsibility
but the process of him actually
functionally moving through that process
really was a process of clarifying what
is this new role right like what does he
still need to own from maybe what his
previous responsibilities were but he
needed to fill out and understand from
his leaders and others what were the key
areas of value that he needed to deliver
and I think so much of that process is
just a process of clarifying the roles
and responsibilities that we have and
also helping our teams do the same which
sometimes we just get thrown in and say
yeah go figure it out without really
clarifying what those responsibilities
are it took him a little while and he
didn't always have the support to do
that and still had to take on and finish
projects from his old role that he was
dealing with and all sorts of things so
that transition process can be difficult
but he had built the skills necessary
because of the ways that he was
operating with for with his teams so
that he was able to be successful even
though perhaps there was a period of
stress through that transition that he
needed to get through before everything
was fully transitioned into the new role
that's useful to know because what
you're really highlighting is of course
even just understanding what the new
role entails and understanding what are
the different steps needed to transition
into it but what about interviewing even
when you are moving maybe internally is
still a new role whether you're moving
vertically or to a different team
horizontally there in my experience
there's always some level of
interviewing involved because you are
working with different people who may or
may not know enough about you and your
skills how does one approach the
interview preparation yeah and sadly
this is one area that I find that people
don't spend much time on because they
think hey I've kind of been there done
that and whatever they throw at me I can
answer those questions
I think there's a lot of opportunity
though for appropriate interview
preparation again you said maybe that's
internal to the company and that
interview may be a little bit different
because people already kind of know you
and your work and that's going to be a
little bit more focused on on those
things and how that applies to the new
role but the process of appropriate
interview preparation is to go back to
some of those personal branding
principles we were talking about earlier
how can you connect who you are what you
bring to the table with really
considering what are the needs of the
organization or the team that you might
be starting to work for right so how can
you connect what are they trying to
accomplish what are they trying to solve
or I love the way they're thinking if
there's an opportunity a job opportunity
or a job role or requisition out there
that's open then that means that there's
a problem that needs to be solved right
how can you understand that problem
and through the process of the interview
frame yourself as the solution to that
problem
okay whether that's you showing that you
have the technical chops to do that
you've worked on similar projects you've
delivered similar types of value and
results that they're looking for but the
more you can understand about what
they're trying to accomplish and what
that problem is that they're trying to
solve the better you can do that now as
far as pragmatically how do we answer
those questions on the technical side we
can't even get into all the different
types of technical questions that
software Engineers can be asked in the
different ways that those interviews are
structured but on the other side
behavioral interviewing still maintains
or continues to be a very very common
interviewing practice these are those
questions that are like tell me about a
time when
and you have this opportunity to tell a
story when you have done something and
helped them move through that process of
seeing how you operate in the situation
or the type of situation that they're
asking about and so far and away the
most effective way to answer behavioral
interview questions is called the star
method s-t-a-r for situation task action
and result and it's just a process of
you being able to share this situation
how can you show the context what's the
situation you were in what's a project
the company you're working in and what's
the criticality of what was going on in
this situation that you're about to
share then the T the task how can you
show what was your responsibility what
were you tasked with and how did you
start moving through that then that
leads to a which is action what are the
steps you and the team moved through
what are the problems that you needed to
solve the better barriers you needed to
break down to solve this problem or move
through the situation and then finally R
is what's the final result and ideally I
would love to see things that are
quantitative can you show we save this
much money we increase quality or uptime
or whatever the metrics are that you're
measuring on we were able to improve by
this much or decrease the problems by
this much and show that you deliver
quantitative value in this situation and
those are the things that an interviewer
is going to remember and all along the
way we can weave in kind of our personal
brand and characteristic traits and
things that we can weave in along the
way as far as the types of skills you
want them to remember that you have the
type of person the team member you are
all along the way we can sort of weave
those in and there's some tactics we
could talk about and get into that I
coach people on all the time to do that
effectively but you want to be memorable
and you want to connect and show them
time that you can do what they need to
do in order to solve the problems and
deliver the value that they need to have
happen
thanks Jeff so I want to now start
talking about the role of mentors as
well as coaches so in our earlier
conversation we talked a little bit
about how do you get over the fear of
the unknown or the unknown you mentioned
you know seeking out people who have
done it before and talking to them
and some of this was covered in episode
281 but would like to you know discuss
that with your perspective as well as
expand this discussion to professional
coaches
how do people find mentors career
transitions are a good point what other
catalysts exist when you feel a need for
a mentor or a coach yeah so hopefully I
hope people always have some form of
Mentor or multiple mentors that they
have in their career and in their lives
because you can have mentors in your
career situation but I have people that
I sort of lean on as mentors as a father
trying to raise a young family right and
different I sometimes have mentors in my
physical health that people who have
done things or know things that I don't
know so now consider medical
professionals to be mentors in some way
right so hopefully have multiple
different types of mentors at every
stage of our life but a career is a big
part of our life so we should absolutely
always have mentors in our careers we'll
talk mentors for a second here but I'm a
big believer in having mentors both
internal and external to the
organizations that we're involved in and
so internal to an organization that can
take a lot of forms from a lot of
organizations will have formal
mentorship programs where they'll pair
you up with someone or you can kind of
put your name in the head out and then
they'll can help you connect or maybe
they just have networking events with
the intent to try and help perhaps
younger Engineers find older more
experienced mentors and those are great
to have those formal things but you can
always ask the question who is doing
things that I'm interested in that I
want to learn about and can I reach out
to them and connect with them right and
so you don't necessarily need to wait
for a formal thing if you see someone
that's doing some interesting things
that you see someone that you want to
learn from you can always take the
initiative to reach out and connect with
them internally right you can do the
same thing externally whether that's
through outside organizations and those
can be professional organizations or
because we volunteer organizations
whatever those look like or just people
in other parts of the industry that you
see hey this person's interesting how
can I learn from them can I reach out to
them and connect with them learn more
about what they're up to and ask
questions what those mentorship related
relationships can look like can be
totally different across the board as
far as they can be really formal you can
have regular meetings or phone calls or
interactions you can just correspond via
email or other digital communication
they can be as formal or as informal as
both of you agree but that's one of the
key things with having meaningful
mentorship relationships is that those
expectations are clarified for both of
you so you can get the most out of it
but that's one more final thing on the
mentor side is I also hope that while
we're seeking for mentors to try and
Learn and Grow personally we're not just
trying to be takers from those
relationships I hope that all
relationships that we build in this case
for mentors as well is we want to be
think transformational in those
relationships that what can I give not
just what can I get out of this
relationship and sometimes what you're
giving as a man and T is just the fact
that you are engaging that you're
following up that you're carrying and
sharing value and really building that
person as a mentor which helps them feel
good and feel like they're giving back
and the fact that you're valuing the
time that they're spending and not just
showing up and then not doing anything
with that that's a way that you can
really give and they're going to enjoy
that and you will as well so don't feel
like you have to have all the contacts
or things to give to them I mean
obviously there's a disparity there is
they're more experienced and have more
connections there but you still want to
be contributing to those relationships
now separate just for a moment coaches
often are paid okay and these can be
paid by your organization some
organizations will actually pay for
coaches to coach people in the
organization whether those are leaders
or technology people people they're
trying to groom they recognize have
potential or maybe they just really care
about this person but there are areas
that they want to grow in or the
individual could say hey I want to pay a
coach to help me work on this particular
skill move through a career transition
level up my leadership capabilities
improve my communication skills whatever
those things are coaches are often
there's often a financial investment
that's involved here right and I think
that changes the relationship in a
little bit but it's it's often positive
because the fact that a person is
financially invested often gets them
being that much more committed to the
process and it also helps the coach side
of things where the coach is also
invested because a coach wins when their
client wins right and so they are
invested in how can I do everything I
can to be helpful and help this person
be successful whereas a mentor is often
most often unpaid and they're just doing
it kind of volunteer because they want
to give back but they're often going to
be a lot more reactive or passive in
their approach to the mentee mentor
relationship whereas a coach will be a
lot more active because there's an
investment in a process that they're
working through through that so it's
just a little bit of the differences
there from my perspective and even being
a mentor it could be just a specific
area of advice that somebody approached
you for like we just want office as well
those are valuable too absolutely
absolutely sometimes it's just one
conversation and anytime you know as a
mentor a mentee like hey can we share
things and deliver value for people and
so if you're in an at a one-time event
and someone asks you some questions at
that event and you're able to share your
experience and expertise and that can be
helpful that's you serving as a mentor
if they want to continue that
conversation and you have bandwidth to
be able to do that then great but if you
don't you don't have to say yes to every
single person who wants to ask you to be
their Mentor right but the people who
you can tell who are really willing to
give to that relationship and they're
hungry for information advice and you
feel like you have a connection with and
those are maybe the people that you want
to focus your time on right as a mentor
what's what's the role of managers in
this in your experience
so managers can be mentors and sometimes
take a little bit of a coaching role in
this
and I hope more and more can do more of
that because even Beyond just like a
formal coach the coaching methodology
and idea is a coach is trying to help
build a person to become the best
version of themselves in many respects
right so a manager
who really recognizes that they have a
responsibility to help and have a
stewardship with the people that they
lead and support
then they might take a little bit more
of a coaching approach rather than a
dictation approach really helping build
the people along the way so managers
often can serve as a mentor to people on
their teams but I would also encourage a
manager to encourage others to find
mentors outside of themselves because
their team is only one perspective of
the types of Technologies and things
that they're working on so getting those
different perspectives and other teams
in the organization again or external is
going to be helpful for them because a
manager also only has limited bandwidth
and also is so closely tied to what that
person is doing with regards to what the
manager is trying to accomplish in the
team and and the projects they're
working on and different things that
they may be in some cases too
emotionally invested in the outcomes and
the things that that person is working
on whereas an outside Mentor or coach
might be a little bit more third party
and only consider what's best for that
person so manager absolutely plays a
role but it shouldn't be the only person
who's serving as a mentor along the way
makes sense and is that also your
experience on people that approached you
with career coaching that they wanted
somebody who was not involved with the
situation 100 a lot of times that's one
of the things that they will say
explicitly I want to talk to someone who
can give me these outside perspectives
and see things that I can't see or are
is not closely tied to wanting to keep
me around or anything here but is just
involved in trying to make the best
decision for me right and so absolutely
that's one of the great values that an
outside Mentor coach can serve is they
have a completely unbiased outside
perspective to try and just help that
person succeed for what's best for them
without any tie to results of an
organization or a team or anything like
that now obviously I will want if
someone's trying to make a career
transition I will want that person to
not just you know leave their previous
organization high and dry right I want
to help them also move through that
transition
gracefully and set the team up for
Success if they are leaving but you know
we still need to consider what's best
for me and where I want to take my
career at this point
so Jeff why did you become a career
coach what was your Catalyst for this
yeah so there's a long story to it but
about five years ago on top of the
engineering and Engineering leadership
work that I was doing I had
opportunities to get into training and
coaching kind of internal to the company
I was working at and a lot of the things
that are basis of the work that I do are
based around mindsets and shifting not
just the pragmatic things that we do but
how we do that how we think about
ourselves and the people that we
interact and that was because of that
work that I got to do
that training and that coaching work
that I got to do internal to the company
because I recognize as I would start
opportunities to do some of that work it
was about five or ten percent of the
work that I was doing I loved it and I
loved those days that I was involved in
that I found a lot of fulfillment around
doing that sort of work and so I started
thinking for myself hey I recognize that
I I'm really excited about this stuff
how can I find ways to do more of this
so this is something that I raised my
hand and I said hey I can do this I
tried it out as a thing on top of my
normal responsibilities and it gave me
exposure to a new way of working and so
then a couple years later I got to one
of those kind of career plateaus for me
where I recognized that I was a point
where I needed a change I wasn't
necessarily delivering my best value for
the organization and it wasn't
necessarily the best place for me to
continue to learn and grow and so we
explored some different options but
eventually got to the decision where I
decided that it was time for me to go
there wasn't really a perfect place for
me in the organization anymore even
though I didn't know what was going to
be on the other side yet and so I spent
a lot of time in reflection and
introspection to try and figure out what
this was going to look like what was my
next step going to be and eventually had
one of these days where I was journaling
and I was writing all sorts of ideas of
what the next step in my career could
look like
and I started connecting principles of
engineering and technology that I had
been involved in and also how that
connected with personal and career
development work and how these different
principles really connected and really
fun ways and I couldn't stop writing I
couldn't stop coming up with ideas and
so that was a little bit of a sign for
me that I said hey maybe there's more to
this and so I started iterating and
ideating on that even more and
eventually decided to take the leap and
and start what has become more than
engineering and doing this work really
combining that pretty broad engineering
experience that I had with this desire
to get closer to helping people so I
like to say that I moved from this
process of developing products and
processes to developing people now and
it's really a joy and an honor to help
people in the work that I get to do how
can people contact you
great question so again we'll we'll
share that resource I talked about
earlier and they can activism there at
www.engineeringcareer accelerator.com se
radio
and stay connected there and by the way
they do need to put those W's in so that
it'll work right and then also I'm
pretty active on LinkedIn that's the
best place to find me Jeff Perry and
Engineering career coach I also host the
engineering career coach podcast so for
other podcast listeners they want to
explore that host that in partnership
with the Engineering Management
Institute if they want to check out that
podcast thank you we'll add that to our
show notes it's been awesome to have you
here today thank you so much for coming
on thanks so much conscient it's been a
great conversation and hope this was an
added value to the SE radio listeners
thanks so much thanks all for listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at sc-radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening